Guide to the Edward Kirby Putnam Papers 1894-1896
University of Chicago Library
Putnam, Edward Kirby. Papers
1894-1896
.5 linear ft. ( 1 box)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Edward Kirby Putnam (1868-1939). Contains notes, syllabi, schedules, outlines, and drafts of terms papers for classes Putnam took as a graduate student in English and sociology at the University of Chicago. Includes classes taught by William McClintock, Oscar Triggs, Frederic I. Carpenter, Edwin Lewis, and Charles Henderson.
Information on Use
Access
No restrictions
Biographical Note
Edward Kirby Putnam, born in Davenport, Iowa, November 17, 1868, received his A.B. degree from Illinois College in 1891. After engaging for a time in newspaper work, he entered the University of Chicago in 1894 as a graduate student in English and Social Science. He remained at Chicago two years before transferring to Harvard, where he took his M.A. degree in 1899; then in 1901 he joined the faculty of Stanford University. In 1906, he left Stanford to become Director of the Davenport Academy of Sciences (now the Davenport Public Museum). He died on May 22, 1939.
Scope Note
The Edward Kirby Putnam Notebooks, dating from 1894 to 1896, are of interest chiefly as they afford a glimpse into the nature of graduate study in English at the University of Chicago in the 1890' s. They show in what manner courses were taught, what materials were used, and what critical approaches were taken. Included in the Notebooks are course schedules, outlines, syllabi, bibliographies, class notes, class reports, and drafts of term papers.
In addition to the English notebooks, there are materials from two courses in sociology given by Professor Charles Richmond Henderson. A special feature of these materials is an extensive listing, with addresses, of British and American settlement houses.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/e/spcl/select.html
Subject Headings
Putnam, Edward K. (Edward Kirby), 1868-1939; Lewis, Edwin Herbert, 1866-1938; Henderson, Charles Richmond, 1848-1915; McClintock, William D.; Triggs, Oscar Lovell, 1865-1930; Carpenter, Frederic Ives, 1861-1925; University of Chicago-Curricula; English language-Study and teaching (Higher); Lecture notes
INVENTORY
- Notebook for English 44 (The Beginnings of the Romantic Movement in English Literature of the Eighteenth Century, Prof. William D. McClintock), 1894. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Notebook for English 49 (Nineteenth Century Literary Movements; Prof. Oscar L. Triggs), 1894. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Notes for class reports in English 49, "Transcendentalism in American Fiction" "Germanic Influences on George Eliot" "Pre-Raphaelitism" "Plato in the 19th Century" "Influence of Keats" (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Notebook for English 51 (The English Romantic Movement, Prof. William D. McClintock), 1895-96. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Notebook for English 83B (English Literary Criticism, Prof. F. I. Carpenter), 1896. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Notebook for English 76 (The Art of the Short Story, Prof. Edwin H. Lewis), 1896. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Drafts of term papers, "The Eve of St. Agnes: A Symphony" "Recognition of the Short Story in Criticism" "Dialogue on Marlowe's Edward II" (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Drafts of term papers, "Nature References in Burns" "Criticism of Fiction in France" "Bickersmith's Use of the Simile in Yesterday, Today and Forever" (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Bibliographies and examinations. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Newspaper account of address delivered by Sir Henry Irving in Kent Theatre, University of Chicago, March 17, 1896. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Draft of short story. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Three notebooks for Sociology 14 (Social Organizations for Promoting Social Welfare, Prof. Charles R. Henderson), 1894; list of British and American settlement houses. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Synopsis of Sociology 31 (Social Conditions in American Rural Life: Prof. Charles R. Henderson), 1895. (Box 1, Folder 13)